Guide to the Caroline Vaughan Photographs, 1977-1992 RL.11510
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Caroline Vaughan photographs
1977-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Vaughan, Caroline
RL.11510
6 Linear Feet 5 boxes; 64 items
Collection comprises 63 exhibit-quality black-and-white photographic portraits of Durham, North Carolina citizens of all races, ages, genders, and sexual orientations, taken from 1989 to 1992 for a Center for Documentary Studies project. Subjects include activists, writers, older people, working class men, friends, couples, and families. Many of the individuals were alumni of Duke University. Also includes several prints and a brochure from an exhibit entitled "Home Ground," featuring Vaughan's family and landscapes from two family farms, 1977-1987. Formats include gelatin silver, Polaroids (some in color), and four palladium/plantinotype prints, along with a hand-pigmented, textured print. The photographs range in size from about 8 3/8 x 10 3/4 inches to 11x14 inches and are all matted, captioned, and signed. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
63 prints; one brochure
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: Portraits and Home Ground.
Biographical Note
Caroline Vaughan was born in 1949 in Durham, North Carolina. After studying photography with John Menapace, she broadened her experience at the Penland School of Crafts, and studied with Minor White at MIT in 1972. She traveled to San Francisco to meet another influential photographer, Imogen Cunningham, and struck up a long-term friendship with her. In 1977, Vaughan was named one of 43 promising young photographers listed in Time-Life's Photography Year 1977. A traditional darkroom printer, she specializes in special formats such as instant camera and palladium prints, and has recently explored digital photography.
In addition to her photographic career, Vaughan has worked as a photography instructor, darkroom technician, and photographer at Duke University.
She was awarded an Emerging Artist Grant from the Durham Arts Council to continue her work with palladium prints, a selection of which she exhibited at Duke in 1986 in a solo show entitled "Home Ground." In 1990 she received funding from Duke's Center for Documentary Studies (CDS) and from Polaroid to produce the portraits of Durham citizens featured in this collection. In the mid-2000s, she re-photographed many of the same individuals, exhibiting their new portraits in a Center for Documentary Studies show, "Personal Disruptions," in 2006.
Her work continues to be exhibited across the United States in solo and group shows, and her prints are part of the collections of the N.C. Museum of Art in Raleigh and other museum and private collections. A selection of her work has been published by Duke University Press in 1986 as "Borrowed Time." Vaughan's work also appears in "Quartet: Four North Carolina Photographers," Safe Harbor Press, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use and distribution requires the photographer's written permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Caroline Vaughan photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase and gift in 1992 and 1993.
Content Description
Collection chiefly comprises 63 exhibit-quality black-and-white photographic portraits of Durham, North Carolina citizens of all races, ages, genders, and sexual orientations, taken by Durham photographer Caroline Vaughan from 1989 to 1992 for a Center for Documentary Studies project. Subjects include activists, writers, older people, working class men, gay and straight couples, friends, and families, Many of the individuals were alumni of Duke University who were involved in sixties activism and remained in the area.
There are several photographers featured in the portraits whose work is also in the Rubenstein Library collections: Peter Goin, Alex Harris, Jeeva Rajgopaul, and Margaret Sartor.
Also includes a smaller series of black-and-white palladium/platinotype prints and a bifold brochure from a Duke University exhibit entitled "Home Ground." These prints feature Vaughan's family members posed in the studio and at two family farms in Oxford, N.C. and News Ferry, Virginia, taken from 1977 to 1987 and printed in 1992 and 1993.
The photographs were taken with large-format cameras and an instant camera (Polaroid), and printed and toned by Vaughan chiefly from 1990 to 1993. Formats include gelatin silver, Polaroids (some in color), and palladium/plantinotype prints, along with one hand-pigmented, textured print. The prints range in size from about 8 3/8 x 10 3/4 inches to 11 x 14 inches and are printed on a variety of papers. Some of the palladium prints feature a circular image format. With a few exceptions, the prints are signed, dated, and matted. Titles were taken from original captions inscribed by the photographer on the prints or mats. Some titles for some uncaptioned prints were taken from the photographer's online gallery. Many prints have data on exposure times, shutter, speed, and other data marked on the back.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Families -- North Carolina -- Portraits; Gay couples -- North Carolina -- Portraits; Gays -- Portraits; Older people -- Portraits; Portrait photographers -- North Carolina; Portrait photography; Working class -- Portraits; Durham (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Color prints (photographs); Diffusion transfer prints; Gelatin silver prints; Palladium prints; Portraits; African Americans -- Portraits; Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Portraits, 1989-1992; 1; 59 prints 4 boxes Gelatin silver and instant camera prints
  Scope and Contents
  The 59 portraits in this series belong to a project undertaken by Caroline Vaughan in 1990 to take a series of portraits of citizens of Durham, North Carolina, emphasizing their commonalities, as well as their diversity in ages, socio-economic backgrounds, race, and sexual orientation. The project was sponsored by the Center for Documentary Studies and by Polaroid.
  Subjects include male and female activists, artists, construction workers, firefighters, welders, photographers, business owners, writers, friends, older people, gay and straight couples, parents and children. They are photographed singly as well as in pairs, sometimes in a trio, typically as half or full standing standing portraits rather than close-ups. Many of the subjects are Duke alumni. One male couple appears in several prints, clothed and nude.
  There are several photographers in the portraits whose own work is part of the Rubenstein Library Archive of Documentary Arts collections: Peter Goin, Alex Harris, Margaret Sartor, and Jeeva Rajgopaul. Also present is a portrait of author Reynolds Price with Nick Shelley.
  The photographs are all traditional darkroom gelatin silver or instant Polaroid prints, taken from 1989 to 1992. There are a few Polaroids in color. All are signed, dated, and matted, and titles have been taken from handwritten captions on the prints. A few were found to be untitled. In some cases their titles were taken from the photographer's online gallery. Also, if the individuals in the portraits were known from other images, their names were added by library staff in a note. Most prints are marked on the backs with exposure times, shutter speeds, and other data.
  - Patsy Bailey, 1991; 11 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0001)
  - Nathan Marvin Bishop [IV], 1990; 11 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0002)
  - Nat Blevins, 1990; 10 x 7 7/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0003)
  - Nat and AG Wood, 1990; 11 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0004)
  - Nat Blevins, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0005)
  - Anne Bloom and her mother, 1992; 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0006)
  - William Holdorf, 1992; 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0007)
  - Jane and Joan Brannon, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0008)
  - R.L. Eurquhart, 1990; 10 1/4 x 11 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0009)
  - James Fallon and David Lloyd, 1990; 11 x 12 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0010)
  - Harold and Anne Frazier, 1990; 11 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0011)
  - Harold and Anne Frazier, 1990; 11 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0012)
  - Anton Foster and Bobby Ellwood Jones, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0013)
  - Henry Caudell [?] and Erica, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0014)
  - Tommy Ray Gilbert, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0015)
    Black-and-white version of color Polaroids, P-0051 and 0052.
  - Peter Goin, Kami [?], and Dana, 1992; 11 x 11 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11510-P-0016)
    Photographer. Collection of his photographs are also in the Rubenstein Library.
  - Alex Harris, Margaret Sartor, and Will, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0017)
  - Jonathan Hexner, 1990; 11 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0018)
    Color pigmented version, P-0054.
  - Alexander Koplowitz, Sidra Makhman, 1991; 11 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0019)
  - Robert McDonald, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0020)
  - Lavelle McNeil and Pat Heath, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0021)
  - John and Lee Murray, 1990; 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0022)
    The copyright date on the print back is 1990. On the artist's website, this image is given the title "Murray brothers, 1980."
  - Roylee and Barbara Duvall, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0023)
  - Alexander Koplowitz, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0024)
  - Alexander Koplowitz, 1990; 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0025)
  - Tom and Merle, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0026)
  - Phillip Pearson and Chuck, 1991; 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0027)
  - Christine Poe, Clinton Poe, 1990; 11 7/8 x 9 1/4 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0028)
  - Charles Powers and Willie Cherry, 1990; 9 3/4 x 13 1/4 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0029)
  - Steve and Andrew Previn [?], 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11510-P-0030)
  - Jeeva Rajgopaul, 1990; 14 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0031)
    Photographer; photographs also in the Rubenstein Library.
  - Reynolds Price, Nick Shelley, 1990; 10 x 12 3/4 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0032)
  - No known title, circa 1990; 10 x 8 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0033)
    From another image on artist's online portfolio, appears to be Andrea Selch, poet, with father and mother. Polaroid version, P-0058.
  - Cathy and Marcus Shell, 1990; 9 1/4 x 12 1/4 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0034)
  - Sue Snedham [?], 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0035)
  - No known title, 1990; 11 x 14 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0036)
    Black man in military camouflage.
  - Erica and Carlton Van Court, 1991; 9 7/8 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0037)
  - Vega Metals, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0038)
    Three men posing with tools. Artist's online portfolio gives title as: "Francis Vega, Neal Carson, Vega Metals, 1990."
  - Tim P. [?] Walker, 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0039)
  - Billy Williams and Claude Reams, 1990; 11 x 14 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0040)
  - Claude Reams, 1990; 14 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0041)
  - Billy L. Williams, 1990; 14 x 11 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0042)
  - Jonathan Williams and Thomas Meyer, 1991; 13 x 10 3/8 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0043)
  - Jonathan William, Tom Meyer, 1991; 10 1/8 x 12 3/4 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0044)
  - No known title, circa 1990; 8 x 10 inches (Box 3, Image RL.11510-P-0045)
    Young construction worker, shirtless, with helmet
  - A.G. and Nat, 1989; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0046)
    Black-and-white Polaroid format.
  - Marvin Bishop, Durham Blueprinters, 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0047)
  - A.G. and Nat, 1989; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0048)
  - Ray, 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0049)
    Black-and-white Polaroid format. Caption inside of mat: "Raymond Lee Eurquhart, Maintenance Mechanic I, age 42, August 9, 1990."
  - Harry and Anne Frazier, 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0050)
  - No known title [Tommy Ray Gilbert], circa 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0051)
    Color Polaroid format. Painter. Black-and-white 11x14 version in collection, P-0015
  - Tommy Ray Gilbert, 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0052)
    Color Polaroid format. Slightly different version from P-0051. Black-and-white 11x14 version in collection, P-0015.
  - Tommy Ray Gilbert, 1990; 10 3/4 x 8 1/2 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0053)
    Color Polaroid format. Vertical orientation. Same subject, black-and-white 11x14 version, P-0015.
  - Jonathan Hexner, 1991; 11 1/4 x 11 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0054)
    Color pigment added to photographic image on deckle-edge thick paper. Version of P-0018.
  - Lee Murray and John Murray, 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0055)
    Black-and-white Polaroid format. Caption inside of mat: "Lee Murray and John Murray, August 9, 1990, Durham Brazing and Welding Co., twins, age 60."
  - Lee and John Murray, 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0056)
    Black-and-white Polaroid format. Caption inside of mat: "August 9, 1990, Lee and John Murray, age 60, metal fabricator and welder, Durham Brazing and Welding Co."
  - Claude Reams, 1990; 10 7/8 x 8 1/2 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0057)
  - No known title, circa 1990; 10 7/8 x 8 1/2 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0058)
    Black-and-white Polaroid format, version of P-0033. From another image on artist's online portfolio, appears to be Andrea Selch, poet, with father and mother.
  - No known title [Claude Reams and Billy Williams], circa 1990; 8 1/2 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 4, Image RL.11510-P-0059)
    Color Polaroid format. Same subjects as in black-and-white version, P-0040.
- Home Ground, 1977-1987; 2
  These four black-and-white photographs of Vaughan's family, including two taken on family farms in Oxford, N.C., and News Ferry, Virginia, were taken from 1977 to 1987 and were printed by Vaughan in 1992 and 1993. At least three of the images formed part of a 1986 solo exhibit by Vaughan entitled "Home Ground," held at the Duke Institute of the Arts, Durham, North Carolina. A fourth bears the date 1987 and may not have been in the exhibit.
  Three of these photographs are palladium prints, and a fourth is labeled as a platinotype print, which is very closely related to the palladium process.
  - William and Mary Vaughan, 1985; 10 7/8 x 12 7/8 inches (Box 5, Image RL.11510-P-0060)
    Palladium print.
  - Son Vaughan, News Ferry, Virginia, 1982; 9 1/2 x 13 inches (Box 5, Image RL.11510-P-0061)
    According to online portfolio title, this print was taken in News Ferry, Virginia in 1982. Format is a palladium print with a circular format, printed in 1993. Original print was exhibited in show, "Home Ground," Duke University Institute of the Arts, 1986.
  - Mother, her sister, 1987; 10 1/4 x 13 5/8 inches (Box 5, Image RL.11510-P-0062)
    Palladium print of Vaughan's mother and aunt. Printed in 1993.
  - Oxford farm, N.C., 1977; 11 x 12 1/8 inches (Box 5, Image RL.11510-P-0063)
    Vaughan's earliest image in the collection, this print has a circular format is labeled "platinotype" on back of print, and was printed by Vaughan in 1992. Original print may have been palladium process, and was exhibited in show, "Home Ground," Duke University Institute of the Arts, 1986.
  - Bifold mailing brochure: "Home Ground, an exhibition of palladium prints by Caroline Vaughan," Duke Institute of the Arts, Durham, North Carolina, 1986 (Box 5)
    Cover image is "Son Vaughan." Print is in collection, P-0061.